Finding Aid for Roy Dikeman Chapin Papers 1886-1945
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Roy Dikeman Chapin Papers
1886-1945
1910-1936
Chapin, Roy D. (Roy Dikeman), 1880-1936.
851435 AC Aa 2
Lansing, Michigan businessman, founder of the Hudson Motor car Company, Secretary of Commerce in the Hoover Administration, leader of the "good roads movement" and the Lincoln Highway Association. Collection includes correspondence, speeches, business papers, clippings and scrapbooks and photographs.
32 linear feet in 33 boxes
7 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 3584 ) was the gift of Mrs. Roy D. Chapin and other members of the Chapin family. The bulk of the collection came to the library in 1940; other smaller additions came throughout the 1940s and 1950s.
The collection is open for research.
Roy D. Chapin, automobile manufacturer and secretary of commerce in the administration of Herbert Hoover, was born February 23, 1880 in Lansing, Michigan. He attended the University of Michigan but did not graduate, leaving in 1901 to join the Olds Motor Works. Desiring to establish his own company, Chapin and other Olds employees went out in 1906 in search of the money needed to produce the car that had been designed by one of their number Howard E. Coffin. They first received financial backing from E. R. Thomas, then later in 1908, when Thomas dropped out of the picture, from Hugh R. Chalmers. The company they formed was Chalmers-Detroit Motor Company.
Within the Chalmer organization, Chapin and Coffin still had dreams of producing the Coffin-designed car. With backing from department store giant Joseph L. Hudson, they established the Hudson Motor Car Company. Originally part of Chalmers, the Hudson became independent when Chalmers bought out the interest of Chapin and Coffin in his company. With this restructuring, Chapin became president of Hudson.
During World War I, Chapin served as chairman of the highway transport committee of the Council of National Defense. After the war, Chapin initiated changes in his company. He introduced a popularly priced car, the Essex, in 1919; in 1922, he began offering closed cars similarly priced to the traditional touring car; and in 1922 also, he reorganized the company's finances which provided new capital for expansion.
In 1923, Chapin resigned as president to become chairman of the board. This move allowed him to devote more time to other interests, such as the good roads movement. Chapin was vice president of the Lincoln Highway Association chairman of the good roads committee of the Automobile Board of Trade, and chairman of the highway transport committee of the International Chamber of Commerce.
In 1932, Chapin was appointed Secretary of Commerce. He served briefly, returning in 1933 to Hudson to take over again as president. Chapin died February 16, 1936.
The Roy D. Chapin papers have been arranged into three series:
Correspondence, 1899-1945 (Boxes 1-29)
Miscellaneous, mostly undated (Boxes 30-33)
Scrapbooks, 1886-1932 (7 volumes).
The Roy D. Chapin papers include correspondence, speeches, articles, interviews, business papers, receipts, scrapbooks, photographs, and miscellaneous notes and files of Chapin's wife, and his biographer, John C. Long, concerning family matters, highway transportation, the automobile industry, general economic conditions, foreign trade, World War I, national defense, state and national politics, the Republican Party, and the University of Michigan. The collection also contains extensive papers concerning the Hudson Motor Car Company, including information on management policies, production, and labor organizing.
Subjects:
Chapin, Roy D. (Roy Dikeman), 1880-1936.; Green, William, 1870-1952.; Hays, Will H. (Will Harrison), 1879-1954.; Henderson, Leon, 1895-1986; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Lewis, John Llewellyn, 1880-1969.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; American Automobile Association.; American Federation of Labor.; Automobile Manufacturers Association.; Battle Creek Sanitarium.; Chalmers-Detroit Motor Company.; Economic Club of Detroit.; Hudson Motor Car Company.; Olds Motor Works.; Republican Party (Mich.); University of Michigan. Student Religious Association.; United States. Dept. of Commerce.; United States. National Recovery Administration.; University of Michigan. Alumni Association.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Library.; Michigan Union.; University of Michigan--Students--Correspondence.StudentsCorrespondence.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1900.StudentsSocial life and customs1891-1900.; William L. Clements Library.; Aeronautics.; Automobile industry and trade--United States.; Balloon ascensions.; Commerce.; Trade-unions--Automobile industry workers--Michigan.; Presidents--United States--Election--1932.; Roads--United States.; Strikebreakers--Michigan.; World War, 1914-1918.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Grosse Pointe (Mich.); United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.
Subjects - Visual Materials
Chapin, Roy D. (Roy Dikeman), 1880-1936.; Durant, William Crapo, 1861-1947.; Duryea, Charles E., 1861-1938.; Earhart, Amelia, 1897-1937.; Ford, Edsel, 1893-1943.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Joy, Henry Bourne, 1864-1936.; Macauley, Alvan, 1872-1952.; Nash, Charles W., 1868-1944.; Olds, Ransom Eli, 1864-1950.; Rickenbacker, Eddie, 1890-1973.; Sloan, Alfred P. (Alfred Pritchard), 1875-1966.; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910.; Wright, Orville, 1871-1948.; Hudson Motor Car Company.; Olds Motor Works.; Airplanes.; Automobile industry and trade.; Automobiles.; Balloons (Aircraft)--1910.
Contributors:
Alger, Frederick Moulton, 1876-1933.; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937.; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965.; Bates, Henry Moore, 1869-1949.; Bezner, Frederick O.; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Chalmers, Hugh, 1873-1932.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Coffin, Howard Earle, 1873-1937.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Dingell, John D. (John David), 1894-1955.; Ferris, Woodbridge Nathan, 1853-1928.; Firestone, Harvey Samuel, 1868-1938.; Fisher, Carl G.; Fleming, Arthur.; Ford, Edsel, 1893-1943.; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923.; Hoffman, Paul G. (Paul Gray), 1891-1974.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Hudson, Joseph Lowthian, 1846-1912.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.; Johnson, Pyke.; Joy, Henry Bourne, 1864-1936.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944.; Lasker, Albert Davis, 1880-1952.; Leland, Henry Martyn, 1843-1932.; Little, Clarence C. (Clarence Cook), b. 1888.; Long, John Cuthbert, 1892-; Meyer, Eugene, 1875-1959.; Murfin, James Orin, 1875-1940.; Newberry, Truman Handy, 1864-1945.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Paley, William S. (William Samuel), 1901-1990; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948.; Putnam, George Palmer, 1887-1950.; Reeves, Alfred L., 1873-; Rice, Grantland, 1880-1954.; Rickenbacker, Eddie, 1890-1973.; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1874-1960.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1887-1944.; Sloan, Alfred P. (Alfred Pritchard), 1875-1966.; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Strauss, Lewis Lichtenstein, 1896-; Street, Julian, 1879-1947; Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981.; Townsend, Charles E. (Charles Elroy), 1856-1924.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; White, Albert Easton, 1884-1956.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.; Woodin, William H. (William Hartman), 1868-1934.; Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence, 1899-1936
  The Correspondence series dates from 1899 to 1936 with some scattering of family and estate materials dating up to 1943. It is the largest series in the collection and concerns family matters, highway transportation, the automobile industry, general economic conditions, foreign trade, World War I, national defense, state and national politics, the Republican Party, and University of Michigan affairs. Correspondents include national and state political and business leaders.
  - 1899-July 1914, 35 folders (Box 1)
  - August 1914-July 15, 1916, 30 folders (Box 2)
  - July 16, 1916-March 22, 1917, 26 folders (Box 3)
  - March 23, 1917-December 10, 1917, 27 folders (Box 4)
  - December 11, 1917-October 21, 1918, 34 folders (Box 5)
  - October 22, 1918-May 31, 1919, 32 folders (Box 6)
  - June 1919-March 21, 1920, 37 folders (Box 7)
  - March 22, 1920-November 30, 1920, 38 folders (Box 8)
  - December 1920-June 21, 1921, 42 folders (Box 9)
  - July 1921-February 24, 1922, 38 folders (Box 10)
  - February 25, 1922-December 30, 1922, 38 folders (Box 11)
  - January 1923-January 25, 1924, 44 folders (Box 12)
  - January 26, 1924-December 5, 1924, 42 folders (Box 13)
  - December 11, 1924-April 30, 1926, 81 folders (Box 14)
  - April 30, 1926-April 25, 1927, 46 folders (Box 15)
  - April 26, 1927-February 10, 1928, 44 folders (Box 16)
  - February 10, 1928-1928 undated, 40 folders (Box 17)
  - 1928 undated-August 17, 1929, 34 folders (Box 18)
  - August 19, 1929-March 23, 1930, 40 folders (Box 19)
  - March 24, 1930-February 10, 1931, 39 folders (Box 20)
  - February 11, 1931-March 9, 1932, 43 folders (Box 21)
  - March 10, 1932-August 9, 1932, 28 folders (Box 22)
  - August 10, 1932-October 10, 1932, 32 folders (Box 23)
  - October 11, 1932-1932 undated, 32 folders (Box 24)
  - 1932 undated-May 31, 1933, 34 folders (Box 25)
  - June 1, 1933-December 31, 1933, 36 folders (Box 26)
  - 1933 undated-August 31, 1934, 33 folders (Box 27)
  - September 1934-December 1935, 35 folders (Box 28)
  - January 1936-1943, 21 folders (Box 29)
  - Letters of thanks concerning the Chapin biography, 1945; 5 folders (Box 29)
- Photographs
  The photographs include images of Chapin's associates in the automobile industry, promotional photos for Hudson Motor Company, pictures of automobiles and auto plants and portraits of Chapin and his family. The scrapbooks series also contains some photographs.
  - Auto Executives, group photos (Box 30)
  - Curtis Aerocar (Box 30)
  - Hudson Promotional Photographs (including shots with Amelia Earhart and Orville Wright), 3 folders (Box 30)
  - Hudson cars, automobile testing, auto workers (Box 30)
  - Howard Coffin with Steamer car, Henry B. Joy, and Miscellaneous (Box 30)
  - Henry B. Joy, formal and informal portraits (Box 30)
  - Henry B. Joy, informal photographs and with family and friends (Box 30)
  - Ford, Henry, 1863-1947 (Box 30)
  - Ford, Edsel (Box 30)
  - Chapin, Roy D (Box 30)
  - Sloan, Alfred P., Jr (Box 30)
  - Olds, R.E (Box 30)
  - Duryea, Charles (Box 30)
  - Duran, William Crapo (Box 30)
  - Macauley, Alvan (Box 30)
  - Nash, G.W (Box 30)
  - Nash, G.W (Box 30)
  - Outsize photographs (Box 33)
    Includes group photos of Hudson Motor Company and auto industry executives, and a composite print of pictures from a cross-country auto trip.
- Miscellaneous Papers and Clippings
  The Miscellaneous series include such things as clippings, a volume relating to his service with the Highway Transport Committee during World War I and personal items.
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 30)
  - Miscellanea (Box 30)
  - Commemorative program (Box 31)
  - School essays, 1895 (Box 31)
  - Scrapbooks, 5 volumes (Box 31)
  - Summary of bills paid, 1918 (Box 31)
  - Notebooks containing receipted bills, 1914-1917 (Box 32)
  - Highways Transport Committee: field organization notebook (Box 32)
  - Diplomas (Box 33)
  - Citations (Box 33)
  - House plans (Box 33)
  - Photographs (Box 33)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbook series consists of seven oversize volumes dating from 1886 to 1946. The scrapbooks are primarily newspaper clippings, but also contain many photographs. The scrapbooks include material on the Hudson Motor Company, the auto industry generally, Chapin's activities with national automobile organizations and his political activities, including service as Secretary of Commerce in the Hoover administration.
  - 1886-1911 (Volume 1)
  - 1911-1918 (Volume 2)
  - 1918-1926 (Volume 3)
  - 1926-1928 (Volume 4)
  - 1928-1932 (Volume 5)
  - 1932-1946 (Volume 6)
  - 1932 (Volume 7)